<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A solemn acknowledgment of publick sins, and breaches of the Covenant, and a solemn engagement to all the duties contained therein, namely those, which do in a more speciall way relate unto the dangers of these times. With two acts of the Commission of the General Assembly of the sixth of October, for renewing the Solemn League and Covenant. And debarring of persons accessory to the late unlawfull engagement, from renewing the Covenant, receiving the communion, and from exercise of ecclesiastick office, with their advice to Presbyteries for celebrating the communion. Together also with, an Act of the Committee of Estates of the fourteenth of October for renewing the League and Covenant</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4259F</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E473_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864668</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79761)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E473[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A solemn acknowledgment of publick sins, and breaches of the Covenant, and a solemn engagement to all the duties contained therein, namely those, which do in a more speciall way relate unto the dangers of these times. With two acts of the Commission of the General Assembly of the sixth of October, for renewing the Solemn League and Covenant. And debarring of persons accessory to the late unlawfull engagement, from renewing the Covenant, receiving the communion, and from exercise of ecclesiastick office, with their advice to Presbyteries for celebrating the communion. Together also with, an Act of the Committee of Estates of the fourteenth of October for renewing the League and Covenant</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, 7-18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>... reprinted ... for Robert Bostock at the signe of the Kings Head in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Novem. 22. 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reprint. Originally published: Edinburgh, printed by Evan Tyler.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643).</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116900:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Solemn ACKNOWLEDGMENT OF PUBLICK SINS, And breaches of the COVENANT, AND A Solemn ENGAGEMENT to all the DUTIES contained therein, namely thoſe, which do in a more ſpeciall way relate unto the Dangers of theſe Times.</p>
            <p>WITH Two Acts of the COMMISSION of the GENERAL ASSEMBLY of the ſixth of <hi>October,</hi> for renewing the Solemn League and COVENANT.</p>
            <p>And debarring of perſons acceſſory to the late unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Engagement, from renewing the COVENANT, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Communion, and from exerciſe of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick Office, With their advice to Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries for celebrating the Communion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together alſo with,</hi> An Act of the Committee of Eſtates of the fourteenth of <hi>October</hi> for renewing the League and COVENANT</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> and Reprinted at London for <hi>Robert Boſtock</hi> at the Signe of the Kings Head in Pauls Church-yard, <hi>Novem.</hi> 22. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116900:2"/>
            <head>A Solemn Acknowledgement of publike Sins and Breaches of the Covenant; And a ſolemn Engagement to all the Duties contained therein, namely thoſe which doe in a more ſpeciall way relate unto the dangers of theſe times.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE Noblemen, Barons, Gentlemen, Burgeſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Commons of all ſorts within this Kingdom, by the good hand of GOD upon us, taking into ſerious conſideration the many ſad afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and deep diſtreſſes wherewith we have been exerciſed for a long time paſt, and that the Land after it hath been ſore wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the Sword and the Peſtilence, and threatened with Famine, and that ſhame and contempt hath been poured out from the Lord againſt many thouſands of our Nation who did in a ſinfull way make Warre upon the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Servants and deſires of his People, and that the remnants of that Army returning to this Land have ſpoiled and oppreſſed many of our Brethren, and that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116900:3"/> the Malignant party is ſtill numerous, and retaining their former principles wait for an opportunity to raiſe a new and dangerous War, not onely unto the rending of the bowels of this kingdom, but unto the dividing us from <hi>England,</hi> and overturning of the work of God in all the three <hi>Kingdoms:</hi> And conſidering alſo that a cloud of calamities doth ſtil hang over our heads and threaten us with ſad things to come, We cannot but look upon theſe things as from the Lord who is righteous in all his wayes feeding us with the bread of tears, and making us to drink the waters of affliction untill we be taught to know how evill and bitter a thing it is to depart away from him, by breaking the Oath and Covenant which we have made with him, and that we may be humbled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him by confeſſing our ſinne, and forſaking the evill of our way.</p>
            <p>Therefore being preſſed with ſo great neceſſities and ſtraits, and warranted by the word of God, and having the example of Gods people of old, who in the time of their troubles, and when they were to ſeek delivery and aright way for themſelves, that the Lord might be with them to proſper them, did humble themſelves before him, and make a free and particular confeſſion of the ſinnes of their Princes their Rulers, their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, their Prieſts and their people, &amp; did ingage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to doe no more ſo, but to reform their wayes and be ſteadfaſt in his Covenant; And remembring the practiſe of our predeceſſours in the yeare 1596. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Generall Aſſembly, and all the <hi>Kirk</hi> Judicatories, with the concurrence of many of the Nobility, Gentry and Burgeſſes, did with many tears acknowledge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God the breach of the Nationall Covenant, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116900:3"/> ingaged themſelves to a Reformation, even as our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors and theirs had before done in the Generall Aſſembly and convention of Eſtates in the year 1567. And perceiving that this duty, when gon about out of conſcience and in ſincerity, hath alwayes been attended with a reviving out of troubles, and with a bleſſiing and ſucceſſe from Heaven; We do humbly and ſincerely as in his ſight, who is the ſearcher of hearts, acknowledge the many ſinnes and great tranſgreſſions of the Land; We have done wickedly, our Kings, our Princes, our Nobles, our Judges, our Officers, our Teachers, and our People: Albeit the lord hath long and clearely ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto us we have not hearkened to his voice, Albeit he hath followed us with tender mercies we have not been allured to wait upon him and walk in his way; And though he hath ſtricken us, yet we have not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: Nay though he hath conſumed us, we have refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to receive correction; We have not remembred to render unto the Lord according to his goodneſs and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our own vowes and promiſes, but have gone away backward by a continued courſe of backſliding, and have broken all the Articles of that ſolemn League and Covenant which we ſwore before God, Angels and men.</p>
            <p>Albeit there be in the land many of all ranks, who be for a Teſtimony unto the Truth, and for a name of joy and praiſe unto the Lord by living godly, ſtudying to keep their garments pure, and being ſteadfaſt in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and cauſe of God; Yet we have reaſon to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that moſt of us have not endeavoured with that reality ſincerety and conſtancy, that did become us, to preſerve the work of Reformation in the Kirk of <hi>Scotland;</hi> Many have ſatisfied themſelves with the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116900:4"/> of the Ordinances neglecting the power thereof; yea, ſome have turned aſide to crooked wayes deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive to both. The prophane, looſe and inſolent cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of many in our Armies, who went to the Aſſiſtance of our BRETHREN in ENGLAND, And the tamperings and unſtraight dealing of ſome of our Commiſſioners and others of our Nation in <hi>London,</hi> the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> and other places of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom have proved great lets to the worke of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſetling of Kirk-Government there, whereby Error and Schiſm in that Land have been encreaſed, and Sectaries hardned in their way. We have been ſo far from endeavouring the extirpation of Prophaneſſe, and what is contrary to the power of godlineſſe, that prophanity hath been much winked at and Prophane perſons much countenanced and many times imployed untill iniquity and ungodlineſſe hath gone over the face of the land as a flood; Nay, ſufficient care hath not been had to ſeperate betwixt the pretious and the vile, by debarring from the Sacrament all ignorant and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſons according to the Ordinances of this <hi>Kirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither have the Priviledges of the Parliaments and Liberties of the Subject been duly tendered, But ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves have laboured to put into the hands of our King an arbitrary &amp; unlimited powre deſtructive to both, And many of us have bin acceſſory of late to thoſe meanes &amp; wayes whereby the freedom and priviledges of Parliaments have been incroacht upon and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects oppreſſed in their Conſciences, perſons and Eſtates: Neither hath it been our care to avoid theſe things which might harden the King in his evil way;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116900:4"/> But upon the contrary he hath not onely been permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but many of us have been inſtrumentall to make him exerciſe his power in many things tendering to the prejudice of Religion and of the Covenant, and of the Peace and ſaftie of theſe Kingdoms; Which is ſo farre from the right way of preſerving his Majeſties Perſon and Authority, that if cannot but provoke the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him unto the hazard of both, nay under a pretence of relieving and doing for the King whilſt he refuſes to do what was neceſſary for the houſe of God, ſome have ranverſed and violated moſt of all the Articles of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>Our owne conſciences within, and Gods judgements upon us without do convince us of the manifold wilfull renewed breaches of that Article which concerneth the diſcovery and puniſhment of Malignants, whoſe crimes have not onely been connived at but diſpenſed with and pardoned, and themſelves received into inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate fellowſhip with our ſelves, and intruſted with our Counſels, admitted unto our Parliaments, and put in places of power and Authority for managing the publicke affaires of the Kingdome, Whereby in Gods juſtice they got at laſt into their hands the whole power and ſtrength of the Kingdome, both in judicatories and Armies, And did imploy the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the enacting and proſecuting an unlawfull engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in warre againſt the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of the diſſent of many conſiderate mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament, who have given conſtant proofe of their integritie in the cauſe from the beginning, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faithfull teſtimonies and free warnings of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, of the Supplycations of many Synods,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116900:5"/> Presbyteries and Shyres, and of the Declarations of the Generall Aſſembly and their Commiſſioners to the contrary: Which ingagement as it hath been the cauſe of much ſinne, ſo alſo of much miſery and calamity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Land, and holds forth to us the griveouſneſſe of our ſinne of complying with Malignants in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our judgment, that we may be taught never to ſplit againe upon the ſame rock, upon which the Lord hath ſet ſo remarkable a Beacon. And after all that is come to paſſe unto us becauſe of this our treſpaſſe, and after that grace hath been ſhewed unto us from the Lord our God by breaking theſe mens yoke from of our necks and putting us againe into a capacitie to act for the good of Religion, our owne ſafety and the Peace and ſafety of this Kingdome, ſhould we againe breake his Commandment and Covenant by joyning once more with the people of theſe abominations, and taking into our boſome thoſe Serpents which had formerly ſtung us almoſt unto death: This as it ſhould argue great mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and folly upon our part, So no doubt, if it be not avoided, will provoke the Lord againſt us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume us untill there be no remnant nor eſcaping in the Land.</p>
            <p>And albeit the Peace and Union betwixt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes be a great bleſſing of God unto both and a Bond which we are obliged to preſerve unviolated, and to endevour that juſtice may be done upon the oppoſers thereof; Yet ſome in this Land who have come under the bond of this Covenant have made it their great ſtuddy how to diſſolve this union, and few or no endevours have been uſed by any of us for puniſhing of ſuch.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116900:5"/>
            <p>We have ſuffered many of our Brethren in ſeverall parts of the Land to be oppreſſed of the common enemy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compaſſion or relief; There hath been great murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and repining, becauſe of expence of means and pains in doing of our duty; Many by perſwaſion or terror, have ſuffered themſelves to be divided and withdrawn to make defection to the contrary part, Many have turned off to a deteſtable indifferency and neutrality in this cauſe, which ſo much concerneth the glory of God and the good of theſe Kingdoms, Nay many have made it their ſtudy to walk ſo, as they might comply with all times and all the revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof. It hath not been our care to countenance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, intruſt and employ ſuch onely, as from their hearts did affect and minde Gods work; But the hearts of ſuch many times have been diſcouraged, and their hands weakened, their ſufferings neglected, and themſelves ſlighted, and many who were once open enemies and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſecret underminers countenanced and employed, Nay even thoſe who had been looked upon as Incendiaries, and upon whom the Lord had ſet marks of deſperare Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy, falſhood, and deceit, were brought in, as fit to manage publick affairs; Many have been the lets and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments that have been caſt in the way to retard and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Lords work, and ſome have keeped ſecret, what of themſelves they were not able to ſuppreſſe and overcome.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe and many other breaches of the Articles of the Covenant in the matter thereof, which it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth every one of us to ſearch out and acknowledge before the Lord, as we would wiſh his wrath to be turned away from us; So have many of us failed exceedingly in the manner of our following and purſuing the duties contained therein, not onely ſeeking great things for our ſelves, and mixing of private intereſts and ends concerning our ſelves and friends and followers, with thoſe things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116900:6"/> the publick good, but many times preferring ſuch to the Honour of God and good of his cauſe, and retarding Gods work untill we might carry along with us our own intereſts and deſignes. It hath been our way to truſt in the means and to relie upon the arm of fleſh for ſucceſſe, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Lord hath many times made us meet with diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment therein, and ſtained the pride of all our Glory, by blaſting every carnall confidence unto us: We have followed for the moſt part the counſels of fleſh and blood, and walked more by the rules of policie then Piety, and have hearkened more unto men then unto God.</p>
            <p>Albeit we made ſolemn publick profeſſion before the World of our unfained deſires to be humbled before the Lord for our own ſins, and the ſins of theſe Kingdoms, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially for our undervaluing of the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpel, and that we have not laboured for the power thereof, and received Chriſt into our hearts, and walked worthy of him in our lives, and of our true and unfained purpoſe, deſire and endeavour for our ſelves, and all others under our power and charge both in publick and private, in all duties which we owe to God and man, to amend our lives, and each one to go before another in the example of a reall Reformation, that the Lord might turn away his wrath and heavy indignation, and eſtabliſh theſe Kirks and Kingdoms in truth and peace; Yet we have refuſed to be reformed, and have walked proudly and obſtinately againſt the Lord, not valuing his Goſpel, nor ſubmitting our ſelves unto the obedience thereof, not ſeeking after Chriſt, nor ſtudying to honour him in the excellency of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor employ him in the vertue of his offices, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king conſcience of publick Ordinances nor private nor ſecret duties, nor ſtudying to edifie one another in love. The ignorance of God and of his Son prevails ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly in the Land; The greateſt part of Maſters
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116900:6"/> of families amongſt Noblemen, Barons, Gentlemen, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes and Commons, neglect to ſeek God in their families, and to endeavour the Reformation thereof; And albeit it hath been much preſſed, yet few of our Nobles and great ones ever to this day could be perſwaded to perform fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duties themſelves and in their own perſons; which makes ſo neceſſary and uſefull a duty to be miſregarded by others of inferior rank; Nay many of the Nobility, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Burrows who ſhould have been examples of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſober walking unto others, have been ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of exceſſe and rioting. Albeit we be the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ingaged to him in a ſolemn way, yet to this day we have not made it our ſtudy that judicatories and Armies ſhould conſiſt of, and places of power and truſt be filled with men of a blameleſſe and Chriſtian converſation, and of known integrity and approven fidelitie, affection and zeal unto the cauſe of God, but not onely thoſe who have been neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall and indifferent, but diſaffected and Malignant, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who have been prophane and ſcandalous have been intruſted; By which it hath come to paſſe that judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries have been the ſeats of injuſtice and iniquity, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in our Armies by their miſcarriages have become our plague unto the great prejudice of the cauſe of God, the great ſcandall of the Goſpel, and the great increaſe of looſeneſſe and prophanity throughout all the Land. It were impoſſible to reckon up all the abominations that are in the Land, but the Blaſpheming of the name of God, ſwearing by the Creatures, prophanation of the Lords Day, uncleanneſſe, drunkenneſſe, exceſſe and rioting, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of apparel, lying and deceit, railing and curſing, arbitrary and uncontrolled oppreſſion, and grinding of the faces of the poor by Landlords and others in place and power are become ordinary and common ſins; And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all theſe things there be many other tranſgreſſions,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116900:7"/> whereof the Land wherein we live are guilty: All which we deſire to acknowledge and to be humbled for, that the world may bear witneſſe with us, that Righteouſneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth unto God, and ſhame and confuſion of face unto us as appears this day.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is needfull for theſe who finde mercy, not onely to confeſſe but alſo to forſake their ſin, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the reality and ſincerity of our repentance may appear, We do reſolve and ſolemnly ingage our ſelves before the Lord carefully to avoid for the time to come all theſe offences, whereof we have now made ſolemn pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick acknowledgement, and all the ſnares and tentations which tend thereunto: And to teſtifie the integrity of our reſolution herein, and that we may be the better enabled in the power of the Lords ſtrength to perform the ſame, We do again renue our Solemn League and Covenant, Promiſing hereafter to make conſcience of all the duties whereunto we are obliged in all the heads and Articles there of, particularly of theſe which follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Religion is of all things the moſt excellent and pretious, The advancing and promoving the power thereof againſt all ungodlineſſe and profanity, The ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and preſerving the purity thereof againſt all error, hereſie, and ſchiſm, and namely, <hi>Independency, Anabaptiſm, Antinomianiſm, Arminianiſm, Socinianiſm, Familiſm, Libertiniſm, Scepticiſm,</hi> and <hi>Eraſtianiſm,</hi> and the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the work of uniformity ſhall be ſtudied and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by us before all worldly intereſts, whether concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the King or our ſelves, or any other whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe many have of late laboured to ſupplant the liberties of the Kirk, we ſhall maintaine and defend the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in all her liberties and privileges, againſt all who ſhall oppoſe or undermine the ſame, or encroach thereupon under any pretext whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116900:7"/>3. We ſhall vindicate and maintaine the liberties of the Subjects in all theſe things which concern their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, perſons and Eſtates.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We ſhall carefully maintain and defend the Union betwixt the Kingdomes, and avoid every thing that may weaken the ſame, or involve us in any meaſure of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion unto the guilt of thoſe who have invaded the Kingdome of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. As we have been always Loyall to our King, ſo we ſhall ſtill endeavour to give unto God that which is Gods, and to <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things which are <hi>Ceſars,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. We ſhall be ſo farre from conniving at, complying with, or countenancing of Malignancy, injuſtice, iniquity, prophanity and impiety, that we ſhall not onely avoid, and diſcountenance thoſe things, and cheriſh and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage theſe perſons who are zealous for the Cauſe of God, and walk according to the Goſpel; But alſo ſhall take a more effectuall courſe then heretofore in our reſpective Places and Callings, for puniſhing and ſuppreſſing theſe evils, and faithfully endeavour that the beſt and fitteſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies may be applyed for taking away the cauſes thereof, and advancing the knowledge of God, and Holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe in the Land. And therfore in the laſt place, as we ſhall earneſtly pray unto God that he would give us <hi>able men fearing God, men of truth and hating covetouſneſſe</hi> to judge and bear charge among his people, ſo we ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Places and Callings Endeavour that Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories and all places of power and truſt both in Kirk and State may conſiſt of, and be filled with ſuch men as are of known good affection to the cauſe of God, and of a blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and Chriſtian converſation.</p>
            <p>And becauſe there be many, who heretofore have not made conſcience of the oath of God, but ſome through fear, others by perſwaſion and upon baſe ends and humane
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116900:8"/> intereſts have entered thereunto, who have after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards diſcovered themſelves to have dealt deceitfully with the Lord in ſwearing falſly by his name, Therefore we who do now renew our Covenant in reference to theſe duties and all other duties contained therein, Do in the ſight of him who is the ſearcher of hearts ſolemnly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that it is not upon any politique advantage or private intereſt or by-end, or becauſe of any terrour or perſwaſion from men, or hypocritically and deceitfully, that we do again take upon us the oath of God, But honeſtly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely and from the ſence of our duty, And that therefore denying our ſelves and our own things, and laying aſide all ſelfe intereſt and ends, We ſhall above all things ſeek the honour of God, the good of his Cauſe, and the wealth of his people, and that forſaking the counſels of fleſh and blood, and not leaning upon carnall confidences, we ſhall depend upon the Lord, walk by the rule of his word, and hearken to the voice of his ſervants: In all which profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our own weakneſſe We do earneſtly pray to God who is the father of mercies, through his Son Jeſus Chriſt, to be mercifull unto us, and to enable as by the power of his might, that we may do our duty unto the praiſe of his Grace in the Churches. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116900:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Edinburgh, 6.</hi> Octob. <hi>1648.</hi> poſt meridiem. Act for renewing of the Solemn League and Covenant.</head>
            <p>THe Commiſſion of the Generall Aſſembly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that a great part of this Land have involved themſelves in many and groſſe breaches of the Solemn League and Covenant, And that the hands of many are grown ſlack in following and purſuing the duties contained therein, And that many who not being come to ſufficient age, when it was firſt ſworn and ſubſcribed, have not hithertills beene received into the ſame, Doe upon theſe and other grave and important conſiderations, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point and Ordain the Solemn League and Covenant to be renewed throughout all the Congregations of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; And becauſe it is a dutie of great weight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, Miniſters after the ſight hereof would be carefull to take pains in their Doctrine, and otherwiſe, that their people may be made ſenſible of theſe things wherein they have broken the Covenant, and be prepared for the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof with ſutable affections and diſpoſitions: And that theſe things may be the better performed, wee have thought it neceſſarie to condiſcend upon a ſolemn ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of publick ſinnes and breaches of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and a ſolemn Engagement to all the duties contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therein, Namely, thoſe which doe in a more ſpeciall way relate unto the dangers of theſe times: And this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn acknowledgement and Engagement ſent herewith ſhall be made uſe of, And the League and Covenant ſhall be renewed in ſuch manner as followes. Firſt, There ſhall be intimation of a ſolemn publick humiliation and Faſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116900:9"/> the ſecond Sabbath of <hi>December,</hi> To be kept upon the next Thurſday and Lords day thereafter, At which intimation the League and Covenant, and the publick acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinnes and Engagement unto duties are to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly read by the Miniſter in the audience of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, And they are to be exhorted to get copies thereof, that they may be made acquainted therewith; And the Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and Faſt is to be kept the next Thurſday thereafter, in reference to the breaches of the Covenant contained in the ſolemn publick acknowledgement, as the cauſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, And the next Lords day thereafter, which is alſo to be ſpent in publick Humiliation and faſting, immediately after the Sermon, which is to be applyed to the buſineſſe of that day, The publick acknowledgement and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is againe to be publickly read, And thereafter prayer is to be made, containing the confeſſion of the breaches mentioned therein, and begging mercie for theſe ſinnes, and ſtrength of God for renewing the Covenant in ſinceritie and Truth; After which Prayer, the ſolemn League and Covenant is to be read by the Miniſter, And then to be ſworn by him and all the people, who are to ingage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for performance of all the duties contained therein, Namely, theſe which are mentioned in the publick acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement and Engagement, and are oppoſite unto the ſinnes therein confeſſed: And the action is to be cloſed with Prayer to God, that his people may be enabled in the power of his ſtrength to doe their dutie, according to their Oath now renewed in ſo ſolemn a way. It is alſo hereby provided, that all thoſe who renew the League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſhall againe ſubſcribe the ſame, And that none be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the renewing or ſubſcribing thereof, who are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the other act and direction ſent herewith.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. KER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116900:9"/>
            <head>Edinb. <hi>6 October,</hi> Post meridiem. Act concerning the debarring of Perſons acceſſorie to the late unlawfull En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement in War, from renewing the Covenant, receiving the Communion, and from exerciſe of Eccleſiaſticke Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, with an advice to Presbyteries for celebration of the Communion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly having found it neceſſary that the ſolemne League and Covenant be renewed after ſo great and evident brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thereof by many in this Kingdom: And conſidering how manifeſtly the Cauſe of God hath been endangered heretofore by too ſudden recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto the Covenant thoſe who have been in actuall oppoſition thereunto, before ſufficient tryall and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence had of their repentance: Doe therefore appoint and Ordaine, That all Presbyteries and Miniſters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116900:10"/> this Church in their ſeverall bounds and reſpective charges take ſpeciall care at the time of renewing the League and Covenant, That none who have had charge in the Army, which under the conduct of Duke <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> engaged in War againſt the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> or with the Forces that were in and about <hi>Stirling</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command of the Earl of <hi>Lanerk</hi> and <hi>George Monro,</hi> or have taken and ſubcribed any Oaths, Bands or Declarations for carrying on theſe ſinfull courſes, or any other Oath or Band condemned by the Generall Aſſembly as deſtructive to the Covenant, Or have been forcers, urgers or ſeducers of others to joyn in the ſaid Engagements and ſervices ſo deſtructive to Religion, or have been active promoters thereof, be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſubcribe, or renew the Oath of the League and Covenant, or to exerciſe any office or power in any of the Judicatories of this Kirk.</p>
            <p>And further, conſidering that it is referred to us from the late Generall Aſſembly to give advertiſement to the Presbyteries of a fit opportunity of celebrating the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and to ſend ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice as we ſhould finde neceſſary for the time; We have thought fit to advertiſe Presbyteries, That the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper may be celebrated after the renewing of the Covenant as Miniſters have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency in their ſeverall Congregations; And that we have found it neceſſary that all who are involved in the aforementioned guiltineſſe, be ſuſpended from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper untill the Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly ſhall take ſuch courſe as they think fit, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the receiving of them unto the Covenant and Communion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116900:10"/>
            <head>Edinburgh, 14 <hi>October</hi> 1648.</head>
            <p>THE Committee of Eſtates being very ſenſible of the grievous back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings of this Land in the manifold breaches of the Solemne League and Covenant, made and ſworn to the moſt high GOD: Doe therefore unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly and heartily approve the ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and pious reſolution of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Generall Aſſembly; for a Solemne Acknowledgement of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Sinnes and Provocations, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the breaches of the Covenant, and a Solemne Engagement to a more conſcionable performance of the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116900:11"/> therein contained, and for renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Solemne League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: And doe require and Ordaine, that the directions of the ſaid Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Aſſembly in their Act of the ſixth of this Moneth for a publick Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of Sinnes and Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Duties be carefully followed, that the Faſt and Humiliation appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them be Religiouſly obſerved, and that the Solemne League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant be ſincerely and cordially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and ſubſcribed in the manner they have preſcribed in their ſaid Act. <hi>Extractum.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Tho: Henderſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
